<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<story-context id="bmad/bmm/workflows/4-implementation/story-context/template" v="1.0">
  <metadata>
    <epicId>10</epicId>
    <storyId>4</storyId>
    <title>Individual File Conversion Controls</title>
    <status>drafted</status>
    <generatedAt>2025-11-09</generatedAt>
    <generator>BMAD Story Context Workflow</generator>
    <sourceStoryPath>docs/stories/10-4-individual-file-actions.md</sourceStoryPath>
  </metadata>

  <story>
    <asA>photographer with files in different formats</asA>
    <iWant>per-file conversion controls to select different target formats for each file</iWant>
    <soThat>I can convert files to different formats in a single batch without running separate conversions</soThat>
    <tasks>
      <task id="1">Add Format Selection Dropdown to File Cards (AC-1)</task>
      <task id="2">Style Format Dropdown and Convert Button (AC-1, AC-2)</task>
      <task id="3">Implement Individual File Conversion (AC-2, AC-3)</task>
      <task id="4">Implement Mixed Format Conversion Support (AC-4)</task>
      <task id="5">Implement Retry Failed Conversions (AC-5)</task>
      <task id="6">Implement Batch and Individual Conversion Coexistence (AC-6)</task>
      <task id="7">Implement Individual File Cancellation (AC-7)</task>
      <task id="8">Manual Testing</task>
    </tasks>
  </story>

  <acceptanceCriteria>
    <criterion id="AC-1" priority="critical">
      <title>Per-File Format Selection Dropdown</title>
      <description>Each file card displays "Convert to..." dropdown showing only valid target formats</description>
      <verification>
        - Each file card displays "Convert to..." dropdown
        - Dropdown shows only valid target formats for the source format (4 options, excludes source)
        - Dropdown disabled during conversion ("processing" state)
        - Dropdown hidden when conversion complete ("complete" state)
        - Default selection: First valid target format (alphabetically)
      </verification>
    </criterion>
    <criterion id="AC-2" priority="critical">
      <title>Individual "Convert" Button</title>
      <description>Each file card has "Convert" button that converts only that file</description>
      <verification>
        - Each file card has "Convert" button
        - Button enabled when file in "queued" state
        - Button disabled during conversion ("processing" state)
        - Button hidden when conversion complete ("complete" state, replaced by download)
        - Button text: "Convert" (no icon needed)
        - Clicking button starts conversion for that file only (not batch)
      </verification>
    </criterion>
    <criterion id="AC-3" priority="critical">
      <title>Individual File Conversion Flow</title>
      <description>User can convert files in any order with proper state transitions</description>
      <verification>
        - User selects target format from dropdown
        - User clicks "Convert" button
        - File status changes: queued to processing to complete/error
        - Only selected file converts (other files remain in queued state)
        - User can convert files in any order (file 3 before file 1, etc.)
        - Batch progress indicator shows per-file progress
      </verification>
    </criterion>
    <criterion id="AC-4" priority="high">
      <title>Mixed Format Conversion Support</title>
      <description>User can select different target formats for different files</description>
      <verification>
        - User can select different target formats for different files
        - Each file converts to its selected target format
        - Download buttons show correct format: "Download XMP", "Download lrtemplate", etc.
        - Downloaded filenames reflect target format: preset_converted.xmp, style_converted.lrtemplate
      </verification>
    </criterion>
    <criterion id="AC-5" priority="high">
      <title>Retry Failed Conversions</title>
      <description>Files in "error" state can be retried indefinitely</description>
      <verification>
        - Files in "error" state show "Retry" button (replaces "Convert" button)
        - Clicking "Retry" re-attempts conversion with same target format
        - Error message clears when retry starts (status to processing)
        - If retry succeeds status changes to complete
        - If retry fails error message updates with new error
        - Retry attempts not limited (user can retry indefinitely)
      </verification>
    </criterion>
    <criterion id="AC-6" priority="medium">
      <title>Batch vs Individual Conversion Coexistence</title>
      <description>Batch and individual conversions work together without conflict</description>
      <verification>
        - Batch "Convert All" button converts all queued files to same format
        - Individual "Convert" buttons convert single files to custom formats
        - User can mix: batch convert 5 files, then individually convert remaining 2
        - Batch progress tracks both batch-converted and individually-converted files
        - No conflict: user cannot trigger batch and individual conversions simultaneously
      </verification>
    </criterion>
    <criterion id="AC-7" priority="medium">
      <title>Conversion Cancel for Individual Files</title>
      <description>Individual file conversion can be cancelled during processing</description>
      <verification>
        - Individual file conversion can be cancelled during "processing" state
        - File card shows "Cancel" button (replaces "Convert")
        - Clicking "Cancel" aborts conversion for that file
        - File status reverts to "queued" (user can convert again)
        - Cancelling individual file does not affect other files
        - No confirmation dialog for individual cancel
      </verification>
    </criterion>
  </acceptanceCriteria>

  <artifacts>
    <docs>
      <doc>
        <path>docs/tech-spec-epic-10.md</path>
        <title>Epic Technical Specification: Enhanced Web UI/UX</title>
        <section>AC-7: Individual File Conversion</section>
        <snippet>Per-file conversion controls allow users to select different target formats for each file and convert files individually or in batch mode. Supports retry for failed conversions and individual file cancellation during processing.</snippet>
      </doc>
      <doc>
        <path>docs/PRD-Path-A.md</path>
        <title>Product Requirements Document (Path A)</title>
        <section>Epic 3: Enhanced Web UI/UX - FR-3.7</section>
        <snippet>Improved conversion flow with format detection, dropdown format selection, batch and individual conversion options, instant conversion less than 100ms, download buttons, and "Start Fresh" to reset interface.</snippet>
      </doc>
      <doc>
        <path>docs/stories/10-2-batch-file-upload.md</path>
        <title>Story 10.2: Batch File Upload</title>
        <section>UploadManager class, file card creation</section>
        <snippet>Provides foundation for file upload handling with UploadManager class, file card components showing filename/format badge/size/status, and grid layout for batch files.</snippet>
      </doc>
      <doc>
        <path>docs/stories/10-3-progress-indicators.md</path>
        <title>Story 10.3: Progress Indicators</title>
        <section>Status updates, download functionality</section>
        <snippet>Implements per-file status tracking (queued/processing/complete/error), updateFileStatus() function, download button functionality, and batch progress indicators for multi-file conversions.</snippet>
      </doc>
      <doc>
        <path>docs/stories/4-3-batch-progress-display.md</path>
        <title>Story 4.3: TUI Batch Progress Display</title>
        <section>Batch vs individual conversion patterns</section>
        <snippet>TUI implementation of batch conversion with worker pool pattern, sequential processing, progress tracking, and cancellation handling. Demonstrates batch/individual conversion coordination patterns.</snippet>
      </doc>
    </docs>
    <code>
      <file>
        <path>web/static/index.html</path>
        <kind>HTML</kind>
        <symbol>Main structure</symbol>
        <lines>1-64</lines>
        <reason>Current web interface structure - shows existing drop zone, status displays, and conversion controls that will be extended for individual file actions</reason>
      </file>
      <file>
        <path>web/js/upload.js</path>
        <kind>JavaScript Module</kind>
        <symbol>UploadManager class</symbol>
        <lines>N/A - to be created in Story 10-2</lines>
        <reason>Core upload management class that will be extended to support per-file conversion, format selection dropdowns, and retry functionality</reason>
      </file>
      <file>
        <path>web/js/converter.js</path>
        <kind>JavaScript Module</kind>
        <symbol>convertFile function</symbol>
        <lines>N/A - existing from Story 2-6</lines>
        <reason>WASM conversion bridge that accepts file data and target format - will be called per-file for individual conversions with AbortSignal support</reason>
      </file>
      <file>
        <path>web/css/components.css</path>
        <kind>CSS</kind>
        <symbol>File card styles</symbol>
        <lines>N/A - to be created in Story 10-2</lines>
        <reason>File card component styles that will be extended with conversion section (.file-card__conversion) for format dropdown and convert button</reason>
      </file>
      <file>
        <path>cmd/tui/batch.go</path>
        <kind>Go</kind>
        <symbol>startConversion, convertBatchCmd</symbol>
        <lines>45-75</lines>
        <reason>TUI batch conversion implementation demonstrates sequential processing pattern and concurrency control that applies to web individual conversions</reason>
      </file>
    </code>
    <dependencies>
      <javascript>
        <package>vanilla-js</package>
        <version>native</version>
        <purpose>No external dependencies - native Web APIs only</purpose>
      </javascript>
      <browser-api name="FileReader API">
        <purpose>Read uploaded file contents as ArrayBuffer</purpose>
      </browser-api>
      <browser-api name="AbortController API">
        <purpose>Cancel individual file conversions in progress</purpose>
      </browser-api>
      <browser-api name="Blob API">
        <purpose>Create downloadable files from converted data</purpose>
      </browser-api>
      <browser-api name="URL.createObjectURL">
        <purpose>Generate download URLs for converted files</purpose>
      </browser-api>
      <wasm>
        <binary>recipe.wasm</binary>
        <purpose>Core conversion engine (existing from Story 2-6)</purpose>
      </wasm>
    </dependencies>
  </artifacts>

  <constraints>
    <constraint type="architecture">All processing must remain client-side (WASM) - no server uploads</constraint>
    <constraint type="performance">Individual conversions must complete in less than 100ms per file</constraint>
    <constraint type="browser">Must support Chrome 90+, Firefox 88+, Safari 14+, Edge 90+ (AbortController required)</constraint>
    <constraint type="dependencies">Zero external JavaScript libraries - vanilla JS only</constraint>
    <constraint type="concurrency">Sequential processing (one file at a time) to prevent memory pressure</constraint>
    <constraint type="ui">Dropdown must show only valid target formats (exclude source format)</constraint>
    <constraint type="state">File status must persist across user interactions (queued, processing, complete, error)</constraint>
    <constraint type="accessibility">Keyboard navigation required (Tab through controls, Enter to convert)</constraint>
  </constraints>

  <interfaces>
    <interface>
      <name>UploadManager.convertIndividualFile</name>
      <kind>JavaScript Function</kind>
      <signature>async convertIndividualFile(fileId: string): Promise&lt;void&gt;</signature>
      <path>web/js/upload.js</path>
    </interface>
    <interface>
      <name>UploadManager.getValidTargetFormats</name>
      <kind>JavaScript Function</kind>
      <signature>getValidTargetFormats(sourceFormat: string): string[]</signature>
      <path>web/js/upload.js</path>
    </interface>
    <interface>
      <name>convertFile (WASM Bridge)</name>
      <kind>JavaScript Function</kind>
      <signature>async convertFile(data: Uint8Array, targetFormat: string, signal?: AbortSignal): Promise&lt;{data: Uint8Array, format: string}&gt;</signature>
      <path>web/js/converter.js</path>
    </interface>
    <interface>
      <name>UploadManager.updateFileStatus</name>
      <kind>JavaScript Function</kind>
      <signature>updateFileStatus(fileId: string, status: string, errorMessage?: string): void</signature>
      <path>web/js/upload.js</path>
    </interface>
    <interface>
      <name>UploadManager.downloadFile</name>
      <kind>JavaScript Function</kind>
      <signature>downloadFile(fileId: string): void</signature>
      <path>web/js/upload.js</path>
    </interface>
  </interfaces>

  <tests>
    <standards>Recipe uses manual browser testing for web UI stories (no automated JavaScript testing framework currently). Testing standards: Manual testing across browsers (Chrome, Firefox, Safari, Edge), device testing (Desktop 1920x1080, Tablet 768px, Mobile 375px), accessibility testing (keyboard navigation Tab/Enter/Esc, screen reader compatibility), performance validation (conversion timing less than 100ms target, UI responsiveness 60fps interactions), cross-browser feature detection (AbortController support check with graceful degradation)</standards>
    <locations>
      <location>web/static/index.html - Manual browser testing</location>
      <location>web/js/upload.js - Manual unit testing via browser console</location>
      <location>web/css/components.css - Visual regression via manual inspection</location>
    </locations>
    <ideas>
      <test-case id="AC-1-format-dropdown" priority="critical">
        <title>Per-file format selection dropdown</title>
        <steps>Upload NP3 file - Verify dropdown shows XMP, lrtemplate, Capture One, DCP (4 options, source excluded). Upload XMP file - Verify dropdown shows NP3, lrtemplate, Capture One, DCP. Verify dropdown disabled during processing state. Verify dropdown hidden when complete state.</steps>
        <expected>Format dropdown correctly excludes source format and shows all other valid formats alphabetically sorted</expected>
      </test-case>
      <test-case id="AC-2-convert-button" priority="critical">
        <title>Individual Convert button</title>
        <steps>Upload 3 files - Verify each has Convert button. Click Convert on file 2 - Verify only file 2 processes (files 1 and 3 remain queued). Verify button disabled during processing state. Verify button hidden when complete state (replaced by download).</steps>
        <expected>Individual file conversions work without affecting other files</expected>
      </test-case>
      <test-case id="AC-3-conversion-flow" priority="critical">
        <title>Individual file conversion flow</title>
        <steps>Upload 5 files - Select different formats for each. Convert file 3 first (not sequential) - Verify only file 3 processes. Convert file 1, then file 5 - Verify sequential processing works. Verify batch progress: 3 of 5 converted.</steps>
        <expected>Files can be converted in any order with accurate progress tracking</expected>
      </test-case>
      <test-case id="AC-4-mixed-formats" priority="high">
        <title>Mixed format conversion support</title>
        <steps>Upload 3 files (NP3, XMP, lrtemplate). Select: NP3 to XMP, XMP to DCP, lrtemplate to NP3. Convert all - Verify each downloads with correct format. Verify filenames: preset_converted.xmp, style_converted.dcp, template_converted.np3.</steps>
        <expected>Each file converts to its custom selected format with correct filename extension</expected>
      </test-case>
      <test-case id="AC-5-retry" priority="high">
        <title>Retry failed conversions</title>
        <steps>Upload corrupted file - Verify conversion fails - Retry button appears. Click Retry - Verify conversion re-attempts. Retry 5 times - Verify no limit on retry attempts. Verify error message clears when retry starts.</steps>
        <expected>Failed conversions can be retried indefinitely without limit</expected>
      </test-case>
      <test-case id="AC-6-batch-individual-coexist" priority="medium">
        <title>Batch vs individual conversion coexistence</title>
        <steps>Upload 10 files - Batch convert 5 to XMP. Individually convert 3 to DCP - Verify both work together. Verify batch progress: 8 of 10 converted. Verify no conflict when triggering batch and individual simultaneously.</steps>
        <expected>Batch and individual conversions coordinate properly with shared progress tracking</expected>
      </test-case>
      <test-case id="AC-7-cancel" priority="medium">
        <title>Individual file cancellation</title>
        <steps>Start conversion - Click Cancel during processing state. Verify status reverts to queued. Verify Convert button reappears. Verify cancelling file does not affect other files. Verify no confirmation dialog for individual cancel.</steps>
        <expected>Individual file conversions can be cancelled cleanly without affecting other files</expected>
      </test-case>
    </ideas>
  </tests>
</story-context>