<story-context id="bmad/bmm/workflows/4-implementation/story-context/template" v="1.0">
  <metadata>
    <epicId>11</epicId>
    <storyId>2</storyId>
    <title>Reference Image Bundle (Portrait, Landscape, Product)</title>
    <status>drafted</status>
    <generatedAt>2025-11-09</generatedAt>
    <generator>BMAD Story Context Workflow</generator>
    <sourceStoryPath>docs/stories/11-2-reference-image-bundle.md</sourceStoryPath>
  </metadata>

  <story>
    <asA>photographer evaluating preset conversions</asA>
    <iWant>three representative reference images (Portrait, Landscape, Product) to preview presets
      on</iWant>
    <soThat>I can see how a preset affects different photography genres before converting my own
      files</soThat>
    <tasks> ### Task 1: Select Reference Images (AC-1, AC-3, AC-5) - Portrait image: Neutral skin
      tones, natural lighting, soft background - Landscape image: Blue sky, green foliage, good
      tonal range - Product image: Neutral background, varied colors, even lighting - Source:
      Unsplash, Pexels, Pixabay (CC0 license verification) - High resolution (2000px+ width for
      downscaling) ### Task 2: Optimize Images for Web (AC-2) - Install optimization tools (cwebp,
      ImageMagick) - Resize images to target dimensions: - Desktop: 1200px width - Tablet: 800px
      width - Mobile: 400px width - Convert to WebP format (quality 80) - Create JPEG fallbacks
      (quality 85) - Verify file sizes (<200 KB each, total <600 KB)
      - Adjust quality if needed to meet file size targets

      ### Task 3: Create Image Directory Structure (AC-4)
      - Create `web/images/` directory
      - Move optimized images to directory
      - Verify directory structure with all image variants

      ### Task 4: Create Attribution File (AC-3)
      - Create `web/images/CREDITS.md` with photographer attribution
      - Document image sources, licenses, original URLs
      - Verify CC0 licenses for all images

      ### Task 5: Implement Responsive Image HTML (AC-6)
      - Add `<picture>` elements to preview modal HTML - Implement
      responsive srcset attributes (400w, 800w, 1200px) - Add JavaScript to switch between reference
      images - Support lazy loading with loading="lazy" attribute ### Task 6: Optional Preload
      Optimization (AC-4) - Add `<link rel="preload">` for portrait image (default) - Test impact on
      page load time - Keep preload if improvement >200ms, remove if negligible ### Task 7: Visual
      Quality Validation (AC-7) - Test images at full size (no pixelation, no artifacts) - Test
      images with CSS filters (Story 11.1 integration) - Test images in before/after slider (Story
      11.4 integration) ### Task 8: Browser Compatibility Testing (AC-7) - Test WebP support on all
      browsers (Chrome, Firefox, Safari, Edge) - Test JPEG fallback on older browsers - Test
      responsive images on mobile devices ### Task 9: Performance Testing (AC-2, AC-6) - Measure
      image load times (desktop, tablet, mobile) - Lighthouse audit for image optimization - Network
      waterfall analysis for lazy loading verification ### Task 10: Documentation (AC-1, AC-3) - Add
      reference images section to README - Document image optimization process for contributors </tasks>
  </story>

  <acceptanceCriteria> **AC-1: Three Reference Images Provided** - Portrait reference image (person,
    natural lighting, skin tones) - Landscape reference image (outdoor scene, blue sky, greenery) -
    Product/Still-life reference image (inanimate object, studio lighting) - Images representative
    of 80%+ typical preset use cases - Neutral starting point (no extreme colors or lighting)
    **AC-2: Image Optimization for Web** - File format: WebP primary, JPEG fallback - File size: <200 KB each (Portrait <150KB, Landscape <180KB, Product <120KB)
    - Total bundle: <600 KB
    - Image dimensions: 1200px width (desktop), variable height maintaining aspect ratio
    - Aspect ratios: Portrait 3:4/2:3 vertical, Landscape 16:9/3:2 horizontal, Product 4:3/1:1 square
    - Compression: WebP quality 80-85%, JPEG quality 85-90%
    - Lossless optimization (remove EXIF metadata, color profiles)

    **AC-3: Licensing and Attribution**
    - Licensing: Public domain (CC0) or created for Recipe
    - No copyright restrictions, no attribution required, commercial use allowed
    - Sources: Unsplash/Pexels/Pixabay (CC0 verified) or Justin's photos
    - Attribution file: `web/images/CREDITS.md` with sources, photographers, licenses
    - No licensing conflicts (no BY-SA, ND, NC restrictions)

    **AC-4: Images Embedded in Web Bundle**
    - Images stored in `web/images/` directory:
      - preview-portrait.webp, preview-landscape.webp, preview-product.webp
      - Fallback JPEGs: preview-portrait.jpg, preview-landscape.jpg, preview-product.jpg
    - No external requests (self-hosted, no CDN)
    - Optional preload for performance: `<link
      rel="preload">` for portrait (default) **AC-5: Images Work Well with Typical Presets** -
    Neutral starting point (not over-saturated, neutral exposure, good tonal range) - Test with
    typical adjustments: Exposure ±1.0, Contrast ±0.5, Saturation ±0.5, Hue ±30°, Temperature ±20 -
    Images representative of real-world usage (skin tones, sky/foliage, neutral backgrounds) **AC-6:
    Responsive Image Handling** - Responsive sizes: Desktop 1200px, Tablet 800px, Mobile 400px - `<picture>`
    element with srcset for multiple sizes - Lazy loading: loading="lazy" attribute - Total bundle:
    Desktop 600KB, Tablet 400KB, Mobile 200KB **AC-7: Image Selection and Validation** - Image
    selection criteria documented (skin tones, outdoor colors, neutral backgrounds) - Visual
    validation (full size, CSS filters applied, before/after slider) - Technical validation
    (dimensions, file sizes, format, browser loading) </acceptanceCriteria>

  <artifacts>
    <docs>
      <doc path="docs/tech-spec-epic-11.md" title="Epic 11 Technical Specification"
        section="AC-2: Reference Image Bundle"> Epic 11 tech spec defines reference image
        requirements: Three images (Portrait, Landscape, Product) optimized for web (<200KB each, total <600KB). Images embedded in web bundle (no external requests). Licensing must be public domain or created for Recipe. Responsive sizes (1200px, 800px, 400px). WebP format with JPEG fallback.
      </doc>
      <doc path="docs/PRD-Path-A.md" title="Path A Product Requirements Document"
        section="Epic 4: Image Preview System">
        Path A PRD defines preview system scope for Phase 1. FR-4.2 (Reference Image Bundle)
        requires three bundled reference images optimized for web, representative of common
        photography genres, embedded in web bundle (no external requests), public domain licensing.
      </doc>
      <doc path="docs/stories/11-1-css-filter-mapping.md" title="Story 11.1: CSS Filter Mapping">
        Story 11.1 implements CSS filter preview logic that will be applied to reference images from
        Story 11.2. Maps Recipe parameters to CSS filter functions (brightness, contrast, saturate,
        hue-rotate). Reference images must work well with these CSS filter approximations.
      </doc>
      <doc path="docs/stories/11-3-preview-modal-interface.md"
        title="Story 11.3: Preview Modal Interface">
        Story 11.3 creates preview modal structure that displays reference images. Modal includes
        tabs (Portrait/Landscape/Product), before/after slider, parameter display. Story 11.2
        provides the actual image assets that Story 11.3 displays.
      </doc>
      <doc path="docs/stories/11-4-preview-slider-interaction.md"
        title="Story 11.4: Preview Slider Interaction">
        Story 11.4 implements interactive slider showing before/after comparison on reference
        images. Reference images from Story 11.2 must work well in slider context (clear visual
        differences when CSS filters applied).
      </doc>
      <doc path="docs/stories/11-5-preview-disclaimer.md" title="Story 11.5: Preview Disclaimer">
        Story 11.5 adds disclaimer explaining CSS filter limitations. Reference images help users
        understand preview accuracy by showing approximate vs. actual conversion differences.
      </doc>
      <doc path="docs/browser-compatibility.md" title="Browser Compatibility Report"> Browser
        compatibility documentation lists Web API support. WebP images supported in Chrome 32+,
        Firefox 65+, Safari 14+, Edge 18+. JPEG fallback required for older browsers. `<picture>`
        element with srcset for responsive images supported in all modern browsers. </doc>
      <doc path="README.md" title="Recipe README" section="Browser Compatibility">
        README documents supported browsers and required features. WebAssembly, File API, Blob API,
        Drag-and-drop events, CSS Custom Properties, Flexbox/Grid Layout all supported. Browser
        support: Chrome 57+, Firefox 52+, Safari 11+, Edge 16+.
      </doc>
    </docs>
    <code>
      <artifact path="web/index.html" kind="html" lines="1-50" symbol="HTML structure"
        reason="Main HTML file where responsive image HTML will be added. Already includes format badges section and upload interface. Reference images will be integrated into preview modal (Story 11.3)." />
      <artifact path="web/static/style.css" kind="css" lines="1-100" symbol="CSS styling"
        reason="Main CSS file for web interface styling. Includes responsive design breakpoints (mobile <768px, tablet 768-1024px, desktop >1024px). Reference images will use responsive CSS for different viewport sizes." />
      <artifact path="web/static/responsive.js" kind="javascript" lines="1-95"
        symbol="Responsive module"
        reason="Responsive design module from Story 2-10 handles touch detection and mobile/tablet breakpoints. Reference images will leverage responsive logic for mobile-optimized display." />
      <artifact path="web/static/main.js" kind="javascript" lines="1-50" symbol="Main entry point"
        reason="Main application entry point imports all modules. Reference images will integrate with file handling and preview display logic." />
      <artifact path="web/static/format-detector.js" kind="javascript" lines="1-80"
        symbol="Format detection"
        reason="Format detection module detects preset format (NP3, XMP, lrtemplate). Reference images show how detected presets affect different photography genres." />
      <artifact path="web/static/parameter-display.js" kind="javascript" lines="1-100"
        symbol="Parameter display"
        reason="Parameter display module shows preset adjustments. Reference images visualize these parameters with CSS filters (Story 11.1)." />
    </code>
    <dependencies>
      <dependency name="None" version="N/A">Story 11.2 has zero external dependencies. Reference
        images are static assets created or sourced with CC0 license. No frameworks, no libraries,
        no external image CDNs.</dependency>
      <dependency name="WebP Image Format" version="W3C Recommendation">Modern image format with
        better compression than JPEG. Supported in Chrome 32+, Firefox 65+, Safari 14+, Edge 18+.
        JPEG fallback required for older browsers.</dependency>
      <dependency name="HTML Picture Element" version="W3C Recommendation">Responsive images with
        multiple sources (srcset). Supported in all modern browsers. Allows serving different image
        sizes based on viewport width.</dependency>
      <dependency name="ImageMagick" version="7.x">Image processing tool for resizing, converting,
        and optimizing images. Used during image preparation (not runtime dependency). Available on
        macOS (brew), Windows (download), Linux (apt/yum).</dependency>
      <dependency name="Google WebP Tools (cwebp)" version="1.x">WebP compression tool for
        converting JPEG/PNG to WebP format. Used during image preparation (not runtime dependency).
        Available via package managers or Google Downloads.</dependency>
    </dependencies>
  </artifacts>

  <constraints>
    <constraint>Image file sizes MUST be <200 KB each (AC-2). Total bundle <600 KB to meet 3G load time target (<2 seconds). Requires aggressive WebP compression (quality 75-85%) and removal of EXIF metadata.</constraint>
    <constraint>Licensing MUST be CC0 (public domain) or created for Recipe (AC-3). No restrictive
      licenses (BY-SA, ND, NC) allowed. All images must support commercial use without attribution
      requirements.</constraint>
    <constraint>Images MUST be embedded in web bundle (AC-4). No external CDN requests, no image
      hosting services. All images served from Recipe domain for privacy-first architecture.</constraint>
    <constraint>Images MUST work well with CSS filters (AC-5). Neutral starting point required (not
      over-saturated, neutral exposure). Must show clear differences when CSS filters applied
      (exposure, contrast, saturation, hue adjustments).</constraint>
    <constraint>Responsive image sizes MUST match breakpoints (AC-6). Desktop 1200px, Tablet 800px,
      Mobile 400px align with responsive design from Story 2-10. `<picture>` element with srcset
      required for proper sizing.</constraint>
    <constraint>Image optimization MUST be lossless where possible (AC-2). Remove EXIF metadata,
      remove color profiles, optimize compression. Balance file size vs. visual quality (WebP
      quality 80 target).</constraint>
    <constraint>Image selection MUST represent common photography genres (AC-1). Portrait (skin
      tones), Landscape (outdoor colors), Product (neutral backgrounds) cover 80%+ typical preset
      use cases.</constraint>
    <constraint>Browser compatibility MUST support WebP with JPEG fallback (AC-7). WebP for modern
      browsers (Chrome 32+, Firefox 65+, Safari 14+), JPEG fallback for older browsers. Test on real
      devices (iPhone, Android, desktop).</constraint>
  </constraints>

  <interfaces>
    <interface name="Preview Modal DOM Structure (Story 11.3)" kind="html-structure"
      signature="modal with tabs, slider, reference images">
      Story 11.3 creates preview modal where reference images will be displayed. Modal includes tabs
      (Portrait/Landscape/Product) for switching between reference images, before/after slider
      showing original vs. filtered images, parameter display showing preset adjustments. Story 11.2
      provides the actual image assets (preview-portrait.webp, preview-landscape.webp,
      preview-product.webp) that Story 11.3 displays.
    </interface>
    <interface name="CSS Filter Mapping (Story 11.1)" kind="javascript-function"
      signature="recipeToCSSFilters(recipe) → string" path="web/js/preview.js">
      Story 11.1 implements CSS filter mapping function that converts UniversalRecipe parameters to
      CSS filter string. Reference images from Story 11.2 must work well with these filters.
      Function maps: Exposure → brightness(), Contrast → contrast(), Saturation → saturate(), Hue →
      hue-rotate(), Temperature/Tint → sepia() + hue-rotate() approximation.
    </interface>
    <interface name="Responsive Design Module (Story 2-10)" kind="javascript-module"
      signature="initializeResponsive()" path="web/static/responsive.js"> Story 2-10 implements
      responsive design with breakpoints: Mobile <768px, Tablet 768-1024px, Desktop>1024px. Reference images use responsive srcset to
      serve appropriate sizes: 400px (mobile), 800px (tablet), 1200px (desktop). Touch detection
      logic reused for mobile image interactions. </interface>
    <interface name="Before/After Slider (Story 11.4)" kind="html-css-pattern"
      signature="slider with clip-path" path="web/css/preview.css">
      Story 11.4 implements interactive slider for before/after comparison. Reference images
      displayed twice (before and after layers) with CSS clip-path revealing filtered version based
      on slider position. Slider handle (range input) updates clip-path percentage. Keyboard
      accessible (arrow keys), touch-friendly on mobile.
    </interface>
    <interface name="File Upload Interface (Story 2-2)" kind="html-css-pattern"
      signature="drag-drop zone + file picker" path="web/index.html">
      Story 2-2 implements file upload interface with drag-drop zone and file picker fallback. After
      file uploaded and format detected, "Preview" button triggers modal showing reference images
      with preset adjustments applied. Integration point: showPreview(file, recipe) function in
      preview.js.
    </interface>
  </interfaces>

  <tests>
    <standards>
      Recipe testing standards for Epic 11 stories:
      - Manual testing required (Story 11.2 is asset preparation, no unit tests)
      - Image optimization validation: File sizes, dimensions, format, visual quality
      - Browser compatibility testing: Chrome, Firefox, Safari, Edge (WebP + JPEG fallback)
      - Mobile device testing: iPhone (Safari), Android (Chrome), responsive breakpoints
      - Visual validation: Full-size quality, CSS filter compatibility, before/after slider
      rendering
      - Performance testing: Lighthouse audit, 3G connection load times, lazy loading verification
      - Documentation validation: README updated, CREDITS.md complete, contributor guide accurate
    </standards>
    <locations>
      - Image source selection: Unsplash (https://unsplash.com), Pexels (https://pexels.com),
      Pixabay (https://pixabay.com)
      - Image optimization tools: ImageMagick (convert command), Google WebP Tools (cwebp command)
      - Image storage: web/images/ directory (preview-portrait.webp/jpg, preview-landscape.webp/jpg,
      preview-product.webp/jpg)
      - Attribution documentation: web/images/CREDITS.md
      - Browser testing: Chrome DevTools (F12), Firefox DevTools, Safari Web Inspector
      - Mobile device testing: iPhone SE (smallest modern screen), Android mid-range, iPad
      - Performance testing: Lighthouse CI, WebPageTest (3G connection simulation)
    </locations>
    <ideas> **AC-1 Testing (Three Reference Images):** - Portrait validation: Person visible,
      natural lighting, skin tones identifiable, neutral background, works with typical presets -
      Landscape validation: Outdoor scene, blue sky visible, greenery visible, good tonal range
      (shadows/midtones/highlights), neutral exposure - Product validation: Inanimate object,
      studio/controlled lighting, neutral background (white/gray/black), varied colors for
      saturation testing - Genre coverage: Verify images represent 80%+ typical preset use cases
      (skin tone adjustments, landscape color grading, product enhancement) **AC-2 Testing (Image
      Optimization):** - File size validation: Portrait <150KB, Landscape <180KB, Product <120KB, Total <600KB
      - Dimension validation: Desktop 1200px width, Tablet 800px width, Mobile 400px width
      - Format validation: WebP primary (quality 80-85%), JPEG fallback (quality 85-90%)
      - Compression validation: Visual quality acceptable (no pixelation, no artifacts at 100% zoom)
      - EXIF removal: Verify metadata stripped (no privacy concerns, smaller file size)

      **AC-3 Testing (Licensing):**
      - License verification: Unsplash/Pexels/Pixabay CC0 label confirmed on source page
      - CREDITS.md validation: All images documented with photographer, source, license, original URL
      - Commercial use: Verify no restrictive licenses (no BY-SA, ND, NC)
      - Attribution requirement: Verify CC0 (no attribution required)

      **AC-4 Testing (Web Bundle Embedding):**
      - Directory structure: Verify web/images/ contains all image variants (3 WebP + 3 JPEG + responsive sizes)
      - No external requests: Network tab shows all images loaded from local domain (no CDN, no external URLs)
      - Preload optimization: Portrait image preloaded on page load (optional), verify load time improvement>200ms **AC-5 Testing (CSS Filter
      Compatibility):** - Neutral baseline: Images not over-saturated, neutral exposure, good tonal
      range - Exposure ±1.0: Apply brightness(150%) and brightness(50%), verify no clipping/crushing
      - Contrast ±0.5: Apply contrast(150%) and contrast(50%), verify improved/reduced separation -
      Saturation ±0.5: Apply saturate(150%) and saturate(50%), verify colorful/desaturated result -
      Hue ±30°: Apply hue-rotate(30deg) and hue-rotate(-30deg), verify subtle color shift -
      Temperature ±20: Apply sepia() + hue-rotate() approximation, verify warm/cool result **AC-6
      Testing (Responsive Images):** - Desktop (1200px): Verify 1200px WebP loaded, file size
      ~150KB-180KB - Tablet (800px): Verify 800px WebP loaded, file size ~80KB-100KB - Mobile
      (400px): Verify 400px WebP loaded, file size ~30KB-40KB - `<picture>` element: Verify srcset
      attributes correct, media queries match breakpoints - Lazy loading: Verify loading="lazy"
      attribute present, images load only when modal opened **AC-7 Testing (Visual Validation):** -
      Full-size quality: Open each image at 100% zoom, check for pixelation/artifacts - CSS filter
      rendering: Apply filters, verify images still look good (not oversaturated/clipped) -
      Before/after slider: Drag slider 0-100%, verify smooth transition, clear comparison - Browser
      compatibility: Chrome (WebP), Firefox (WebP), Safari (WebP), Edge (WebP), Safari 13 (JPEG
      fallback) - Mobile devices: iPhone (Safari), Android (Chrome), iPad (Safari) - verify correct
      sizes loaded **Performance Testing:** - 3G load time: Measure total load time on WebPageTest
      (3G connection), target <2 seconds
      - Lighthouse audit: Run Lighthouse, verify "Serve images in next-gen formats" passes, "Properly size images" passes, "Defer offscreen images" passes
      - Network waterfall: DevTools Network tab, verify images load only when modal opened (lazy loading)

      **Edge Cases:**
      - JPEG fallback: Test on Safari 13 or older, verify JPEG loads correctly
      - Extremely small screens (<320px): Verify images scale down correctly, remain readable
      - Slow connections (2G): Verify images load eventually, no broken image icons
      - Orientation change (mobile): Portrait → Landscape, verify images reflow correctly
    </ideas>
  </tests>
</story-context>