<story-context id="bmad/bmm/workflows/4-implementation/story-context/template" v="1.0">
  <metadata>
    <epicId>11</epicId>
    <storyId>5</storyId>
    <title>Clear Disclaimer About CSS Filter Approximation</title>
    <status>drafted</status>
    <generatedAt>2025-11-09</generatedAt>
    <generator>BMAD Story Context Workflow</generator>
    <sourceStoryPath>docs/stories/11-5-preview-disclaimer.md</sourceStoryPath>
  </metadata>

  <story>
    <asA>photographer evaluating preset previews</asA>
    <iWant>clear communication about the limitations of CSS filter-based previews</iWant>
    <soThat>I understand the preview is approximate and set appropriate expectations for the actual
      conversion</soThat>
    <tasks>
      ### Task 1: Add Disclaimer Label to Modal (AC-1)
      - Update modal HTML in web/index.html with disclaimer label
      - Add disclaimer CSS in web/css/modal.css

      ### Task 2: Implement Tooltip Functionality (AC-2)
      - Add tooltip JavaScript in web/js/disclaimer.js
      - Add tooltip CSS with desktop and mobile variants

      ### Task 3: Review UI Copy for Misleading Claims (AC-3)
      - Audit all modal text for misleading terms
      - Replace any misleading terms with neutral phrasing
      - Add neutral phrasing guide to docs

      ### Task 4: Add Documentation Section (AC-4)
      - Create docs/preview-limitations.md with technical details
      - Add FAQ entry to docs/FAQ.md

      ### Task 5: List Preview Limitations in README (AC-5)
      - Add Preview System section to README.md with limitations table
      - Document roadmap (Phase 1-3)

      ### Task 6: First-Time User Guidance (AC-6, Optional)
      - Add first-time tooltip logic with localStorage

      ### Task 7: Manual Testing
      - Visual, tooltip, UI copy audit, documentation review

      ### Task 8: Accessibility Testing
      - Screen reader, keyboard navigation, color contrast testing

      ### Task 9: Documentation Updates
      - Update docs/index.md, landing page FAQ, cross-references

      ### Task 10: Community Transparency
      - GitHub README honesty, issue template, CONTRIBUTING.md notes
    </tasks>
  </story>

  <acceptanceCriteria>
    **AC-1: Prominent Disclaimer Label in Modal**
    - Disclaimer label visible in preview modal with warning/info badge style
    - Text: "⚠️ Approximate preview using CSS filters"
    - Position: Top of modal or below slider
    - Style: Yellow/blue background, icon, readable text (14px minimum)
    - Label always visible (persistent, not dismissible)
    - Visible on all tabs (Portrait, Landscape, Product)
    - Visual prominence with WCAG AA 4.5:1 contrast minimum

    **AC-2: Tooltip/Help Text Explains Limitations**
    - Tooltip triggered by hover, tap, or keyboard (Enter/Space)
    - Content explains CSS filter limitations (tone curves, advanced color, white balance)
    - Placement: Below label (desktop), bottom banner (mobile)
    - Auto-dismisses after 5 seconds or on click outside
    - Accessibility: aria-describedby, screen reader support, Esc key dismissal

    **AC-3: No Misleading Claims About Preview Accuracy**
    - Avoid misleading terms ("realistic", "accurate", "true", "exact")
    - Use neutral terms ("approximate", "CSS filter-based", "quick comparison")
    - UI copy review of all modal text
    - User expectations managed through honest communication

    **AC-4: Documentation Explains Preview vs. Actual Conversion Differences**
    - README section: "Preview System Limitations"
    - FAQ entry: "Why doesn't my preview match the converted file exactly?"
    - Comparison table showing preview vs. actual conversion for each parameter

    **AC-5: Preview Limitations Listed in Documentation**
    - Explicit limitations section with 4 limitations documented
    - Phase roadmap (Phase 1: CSS filters, Phase 2: Canvas, Phase 3: WebGL)

    **AC-6: User Expectations Managed Through Transparent Communication**
    - Modal disclaimer sets expectations (preview = approximate, actual = final)
    - First-time user guidance (optional tooltip auto-show)
    - "Try a sample conversion" CTA
    - Community transparency in GitHub README and issue templates
  </acceptanceCriteria>

  <artifacts>
    <docs>
      <doc path="docs/tech-spec-epic-11.md" title="Epic 11 Technical Specification"
        section="AC-4: Accuracy Communication">
        Epic 11 tech spec defines accuracy communication requirements for preview disclaimer. AC-4
        specifies: Label "Approximate preview using CSS filters" (prominent in modal), tooltip/help
        text explains CSS filter limitations, no misleading claims, documentation explains preview
        vs. actual conversion differences, preview limitations listed.
      </doc>
      <doc path="docs/PRD-Path-A.md" title="Path A Product Requirements Document"
        section="Epic 4: Image Preview System">
        Path A PRD defines preview system scope for Phase 1. FR-4.4 (Accuracy Communication)
        requires clear disclaimer, tooltip explaining limitations, no misleading claims,
        documentation explaining differences, transparent communication. Preview accuracy emphasized
        as approximate, not pixel-perfect.
      </doc>
      <doc path="docs/stories/11-3-preview-modal-interface.md"
        title="Story 11.3: Preview Modal Interface">
        Story 11.3 creates preview modal structure where disclaimer will be placed. Modal includes
        tabs (Portrait/Landscape/Product), before/after slider, parameter display, and action
        buttons. Disclaimer will be integrated at top of modal.
      </doc>
      <doc path="docs/stories/11-1-css-filter-mapping.md" title="Story 11.1: CSS Filter Mapping">
        Story 11.1 implements CSS filter preview logic that disclaimer references. Maps Recipe
        parameters to CSS filter functions (brightness, contrast, saturate, hue-rotate). Disclaimer
        explains these are approximations with known limitations (tone curves, advanced color
        grading).
      </doc>
      <doc path="docs/FAQ.md" title="Recipe FAQ" section="Conversion Quality">
        Existing FAQ structure and style guide for adding preview limitation question. Current FAQ
        covers legal, privacy, conversion accuracy (98%+ for core adjustments), format limitations,
        browser compatibility. New entry: "Why doesn't my preview match the converted file exactly?"
      </doc>
      <doc path="README.md" title="Recipe README" section="Format Compatibility">
        README includes format compatibility section and frequently asked questions. Preview
        limitations section will be added documenting Phase 1 CSS filter approach,
        supported/unsupported parameters, and Phase 2-3 roadmap.
      </doc>
      <doc path="docs/stories/7-4-legal-disclaimer.md" title="Story 7.4: Legal Disclaimer">
        Story 7.4 established pattern for disclaimer sections on landing page. Used MIT License base
        with custom disclosures, light yellow background (#fff8e1), orange accent, legal-caps class
        for warranty text. Preview disclaimer will follow similar transparency patterns.
      </doc>
      <doc path="docs/browser-compatibility.md" title="Browser Compatibility Report">
        Browser compatibility documentation lists supported browsers and Web API support. CSS
        Filters supported in Chrome 57+, Firefox 52+, Safari 11+, Edge 16+. Preview disclaimer will
        reference these minimum requirements.
      </doc>
    </docs>
    <code>
      <artifact path="web/index.html" kind="html" lines="172-261" symbol="legal-disclaimer section"
        reason="Existing legal disclaimer section provides template for disclaimer structure and styling patterns. Preview disclaimer modal will follow similar transparency approach with warning badge style." />
      <artifact path="web/static/style.css" kind="css" lines="1795-1906"
        symbol="legal-section styles"
        reason="Legal disclaimer CSS defines warning badge styles, subsection formatting, responsive breakpoints. Preview disclaimer modal will reuse color scheme (yellow background, orange accent) and responsive patterns." />
      <artifact path="web/static/style.css" kind="css" lines="1654-1730"
        symbol="unsupported-browser screen"
        reason="Unsupported browser screen (Story 6-4 AC-7) shows full-page message pattern with gradient background and centered content. Preview disclaimer tooltip for mobile can use similar full-width bottom banner approach." />
      <artifact path="web/static/style.css" kind="css" lines="1144-1195"
        symbol="error handling styles"
        reason="Error details toggle and collapsible content styles show pattern for expandable help text. Preview disclaimer tooltip can follow similar interaction pattern (click to expand details)." />
      <artifact path="web/static/style.css" kind="css" lines="349-355" symbol="disclaimer class"
        reason="Existing disclaimer class in privacy-messaging module shows footer disclaimer pattern. Preview modal disclaimer will use different placement (prominent in modal) but can reference styling consistency." />
    </code>
    <dependencies>
      <dependency name="None" version="N/A">Story 11.5 has zero external dependencies. Uses
        browser-native HTML, CSS, and JavaScript only. No frameworks, no libraries, no external
        resources.</dependency>
      <dependency name="CSS Filters Level 1" version="W3C Recommendation">Browser-native CSS filter
        functions used for preview. Supported in all modern browsers (Chrome 57+, Firefox 52+,
        Safari 11+, Edge 16+).</dependency>
      <dependency name="WCAG 2.1 Level AA" version="W3C Recommendation">Accessibility standard for
        color contrast (4.5:1 minimum for text), keyboard navigation, screen reader support, and
        ARIA attributes.</dependency>
      <dependency name="localStorage API" version="Web Storage API">Browser API for storing
        first-time user preference (optional Task 6). Supported universally in modern browsers.</dependency>
    </dependencies>
  </artifacts>

  <constraints>
    <constraint>Disclaimer label MUST be persistent and non-dismissible (AC-1). Users cannot hide or
      close the disclaimer - always visible in modal to maintain transparency about preview
      limitations.</constraint>
    <constraint>No misleading terminology allowed (AC-3). Must avoid terms like "realistic",
      "accurate", "true preview", "exact preview", "pixel-perfect" that overpromise preview
      accuracy.</constraint>
    <constraint>Color contrast MUST meet WCAG AA 4.5:1 minimum (AC-1, AC-8). Disclaimer label text
      must be readable against background for users with visual impairments.</constraint>
    <constraint>Tooltip MUST be keyboard accessible (AC-2, AC-8). Esc key dismisses, Enter/Space
      shows tooltip, Tab key navigates to disclaimer label.</constraint>
    <constraint>Mobile tooltip uses full-width bottom banner (AC-2). Desktop uses popover below
      label, mobile uses bottom sheet for better touch interaction.</constraint>
    <constraint>Documentation MUST explain preview vs. actual conversion differences (AC-4).
      Comparison table required showing which parameters are accurate (Exposure, Contrast,
      Saturation, Hue) vs. approximated (Temperature/Tint) vs. not supported (Tone Curves).</constraint>
    <constraint>Preview limitations MUST be explicitly listed (AC-5). Four specific limitations
      documented: (1) Tone curves not supported, (2) Advanced color grading approximated, (3) White
      balance approximated, (4) Browser support varies.</constraint>
    <constraint>Phase roadmap MUST be transparent (AC-5). Phase 1 (Current): CSS filters, Phase 2
      (Future): Canvas API with tone curves, Phase 3 (Future): WebGL pixel-perfect.</constraint>
    <constraint>Zero tracking/analytics allowed (AC-6). First-time tooltip preference stored in
      localStorage only (client-side), no server transmission.</constraint>
  </constraints>

  <interfaces>
    <interface name="Preview Modal DOM Structure (Story 11.3)" kind="html-structure"
      signature="modal with tabs, slider, disclaimer label">
      Preview modal created in Story 11.3 provides DOM structure for integrating disclaimer. Modal
      includes header, tabs, slider, parameter display, and action buttons. Disclaimer label will be
      inserted after header, before tabs.
    </interface>
    <interface name="CSS Filter Mapping (Story 11.1)" kind="javascript-function"
      signature="recipeToCSSFilters(recipe) → string" path="web/js/preview.js">
      Story 11.1 implements CSS filter mapping function that disclaimer references. Function
      converts UniversalRecipe parameters to CSS filter string. Disclaimer explains this approach
      has limitations (tone curves, advanced color grading not supported).
    </interface>
    <interface name="Legal Disclaimer Pattern (Story 7.4)" kind="html-css-pattern"
      signature="warning badge + subsections + responsive layout" path="web/index.html:172-261">
      Story 7.4 established pattern for disclaimer sections: yellow background (#fff8e1), orange
      accent (#f59e0b), subsection structure, legal-caps class, responsive breakpoints. Preview
      disclaimer will follow similar visual language for consistency.
    </interface>
    <interface name="Error Handling UI (Story 2.8)" kind="html-css-pattern"
      signature="collapsible error details + toggle button" path="web/static/style.css:1144-1195">
      Story 2.8 implements collapsible error details pattern. Preview disclaimer tooltip can follow
      similar interaction (click to expand detailed explanation). Toggle button pattern reusable for
      tooltip trigger.
    </interface>
    <interface name="Privacy Messaging (Story 2.9)" kind="html-css-pattern"
      signature="status messages + FAQ collapsible" path="web/static/style.css:349-355">
      Story 2.9 establishes privacy status message patterns. Preview disclaimer aligns with Recipe's
      transparency philosophy (privacy-first, honest communication). Similar tone and visual
      treatment (info badge, clear messaging).
    </interface>
  </interfaces>

  <tests>
    <standards>
      Recipe testing standards for Epic 11 stories:
      - Manual testing required (Story 11.5 is UI-focused, no unit tests)
      - Browser compatibility testing: Chrome, Firefox, Safari, Edge (latest 2 versions)
      - Mobile device testing: iPhone (Safari), Android (Chrome), responsive breakpoints
      - Accessibility testing: Screen reader (NVDA/VoiceOver), keyboard navigation, color contrast
      (WebAIM tools)
      - Visual regression: Compare disclaimer appearance across browsers, check WCAG AA compliance
      - Documentation validation: Verify README, FAQ, preview-limitations.md complete and accurate
    </standards>
    <locations>
      - Manual browser testing: Chrome DevTools (F12), Firefox DevTools, Safari Web Inspector
      - Screen reader testing: NVDA (Windows), VoiceOver (macOS/iOS)
      - Color contrast testing: WebAIM Contrast Checker
      (https://webaim.org/resources/contrastchecker/)
      - Mobile device testing: iPhone SE (smallest modern screen), Android mid-range, iPad
      - Documentation review: docs/README.md, docs/FAQ.md, docs/preview-limitations.md (to be
      created)
    </locations>
    <ideas> **AC-1 Testing (Disclaimer Label Visibility):** - Visual inspection: Label visible in
      modal at correct position (top or below slider) - Color contrast: Use WebAIM checker to verify
      Yellow-100 background (#FEF3C7) with Yellow-900 text (#78350F) meets 4.5:1 WCAG AA minimum -
      Persistence: Verify label always visible (not hidden on tab switching, slider interaction, or
      modal resize) - Responsive: Test at 3 breakpoints (mobile <768px, tablet 768-1024px, desktop>1024px) **AC-2 Testing (Tooltip
      Functionality):** - Hover: Mouse hover over disclaimer label shows tooltip below (desktop) -
      Click: Tap/click disclaimer label shows tooltip (mobile/desktop) - Keyboard: Tab to label,
      press Enter/Space shows tooltip, press Esc dismisses - Auto-dismiss: Tooltip disappears after
      10 seconds (verify with timer) - Click outside: Click outside tooltip dismisses it - Mobile:
      Verify tooltip shows as full-width bottom banner (not popover) **AC-3 Testing (No Misleading
      Claims):** - Text audit: Search codebase for "realistic", "accurate", "true", "exact",
      "perfect" in modal context - Replace violations: Ensure all modal text uses "approximate",
      "CSS filter-based", "quick comparison" - Documentation review: README, FAQ use neutral
      phrasing (no overpromising) **AC-4 Testing (Documentation Complete):** - README section:
      "Preview System Limitations" exists with comparison table - FAQ entry: "Why doesn't my preview
      match?" answered with technical explanation - Comparison table: Shows preview vs. actual
      conversion for each parameter (Exposure, Contrast, Saturation, Hue, Temperature/Tint, Tone
      Curves, Advanced Color) **AC-5 Testing (Limitations Listed):** - Explicit limitations: Verify
      4 limitations documented (tone curves, advanced color, white balance, browser support) - Phase
      roadmap: Phase 1 (CSS filters), Phase 2 (Canvas), Phase 3 (WebGL) documented in README and
      docs/preview-limitations.md **AC-6 Testing (User Expectation Management):** - Modal
      disclaimer: Sets expectations (preview = approximate, actual = final) - First-time tooltip:
      Auto-shows on first modal open, localStorage preference saves "Don't show again" - Community
      transparency: GitHub README honest about limitations, issue template asks for sample files
      **Accessibility Testing (AC-8):** - Screen reader: Disclaimer label announced as "Warning:
      Approximate preview using CSS filters" - Keyboard navigation: Tab to label, Enter shows
      tooltip, Esc dismisses, arrow keys navigate modal - Focus visible: Clear outline on disclaimer
      label when focused - ARIA attributes: aria-describedby links label to tooltip, aria-live
      region for tooltip visibility changes - Color contrast: Yellow-100 background (#FEF3C7) with
      Yellow-900 text (#78350F) = 8.2:1 (exceeds WCAG AAA 7:1) **Edge Cases:** - Modal opened twice:
      Ensure only one modal instance (close previous) - Tooltip shown twice: Ensure only one tooltip
      visible (hide previous) - Slider dragging while tooltip open: Tooltip remains visible (not
      dismissed by slider interaction) - Tab switching while tooltip open: Tooltip remains visible
      (persists across tab changes) - Mobile orientation change: Tooltip repositions correctly
      (portrait → landscape) - localStorage disabled: First-time tooltip still works (graceful
      degradation, shows every time) - Extremely small screens (<320px): Disclaimer text wraps correctly, remains readable
    </ideas>
  </tests>
</story-context>