<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<story-context id="bmad/bmm/workflows/4-implementation/story-context/template" v="1.0">
  <metadata>
    <epicId>5</epicId>
    <storyId>2</storyId>
    <title>Binary Structure Visualization</title>
    <status>drafted</status>
    <generatedAt>2025-11-06</generatedAt>
    <generator>BMAD Story Context Workflow</generator>
    <sourceStoryPath>docs/stories/5-2-binary-structure-visualization.md</sourceStoryPath>
  </metadata>

  <story>
    <asA>developer or advanced user contributing to Recipe reverse engineering efforts</asA>
    <iWant>to view NP3 binary files as annotated hex dumps with field labels and byte offsets</iWant>
    <soThat>I can understand the internal structure of Picture Control files, validate parsing logic, and contribute to format documentation</soThat>
    <tasks>
Task 1: Create Binary Dump Function - Create internal/inspect/binary.go file, define np3FieldMap constant with minimum 8 required fields from Epic 1 parser, implement BinaryDump function with format validation, field value normalization formulas, add unit tests for hex formatting and field annotation.

Task 2: Integrate Binary Mode into CLI - Update cmd/cli/inspect.go with --binary flag, implement binary mode logic in runInspect with NP3 validation, add format validation with helpful error messages for XMP/lrtemplate, update help text, add CLI integration tests.

Task 3: Enhance Field Map with Epic 1 Knowledge - Review internal/formats/np3/parse.go for all known byte positions, expand np3FieldMap with comprehensive field list, create formatFieldValue function with normalization, add multi-byte field support, test with all NP3 sample files.

Task 4: Performance Optimization - Create internal/inspect/binary_test.go file, implement benchmark tests, run benchmarks to validate under 10ms target, optimize using strings.Builder and pre-allocated buffers, profile memory usage to verify under 5 MB target.

Task 5: Error Handling and Graceful Degradation - Implement format validation with clear errors for non-NP3 formats, add magic bytes validation with graceful warnings, handle incomplete files with partial annotations, add comprehensive error tests.

Task 6: Documentation and Integration - Update README with binary mode examples and Binary Structure Visualization section, update help text with command descriptions and examples, add to Makefile, create example hex dump for documentation, perform end-to-end testing with all three formats.
    </tasks>
  </story>

  <acceptanceCriteria>
AC-1: Hex Dump with Byte Offsets - recipe inspect FILE --binary outputs hex dump with hexadecimal byte offsets, each line format [0xOFFSET] HEX_BYTES FIELD_NAME (VALUE), offsets increment correctly, hex bytes in groups of 2, full file coverage.

AC-2: Known Field Annotations - All documented NP3 fields labeled, minimum fields Magic bytes Version Contrast Brightness Saturation Hue Sharpness Preset Name, field values in human-readable form with normalization, unknown bytes shown as raw hex, field map defined in internal/inspect/binary.go.

AC-3: NP3-Only Validation - --binary flag only works with NP3 files, clear error messages for XMP and lrtemplate explaining text format nature, suggests using JSON mode instead.

AC-4: Output Format Control - --output FILE flag saves dump to file instead of stdout, correct file permissions 0644, overwrites without confirmation, creates parent directories, output is plain text.

AC-5: Performance Requirement - Binary dump completes in under 10ms for typical NP3 files under 50KB, memory usage under 5 MB, no parsing overhead on raw bytes, benchmark tests validate targets, faster than JSON mode.

AC-6: Error Handling - File read errors identify problematic file path, invalid format errors user-friendly, corrupt NP3 files produce partial hex dump with warnings, graceful degradation for unknown fields, Unix exit code conventions.
  </acceptanceCriteria>

  <artifacts>
    <docs>
      <artifact>
        <path>docs/PRD.md</path>
        <title>Product Requirements Document</title>
        <section>FR-5.2 Binary Structure Visualization</section>
        <snippet>Recipe universal photo preset converter for Nikon Z-series cameras. FR-5.2 specifies binary visualization tool for NP3 files showing annotated hex dumps with field labels and byte offsets for reverse engineering support.</snippet>
      </artifact>
      <artifact>
        <path>docs/tech-spec-epic-5.md</path>
        <title>Epic Technical Specification Data Extraction and Inspection</title>
        <section>AC-2 Binary Structure Visualization</section>
        <snippet>Binary visualization provides transparency tools revealing file structure internals. Hex dump format [0xOFFSET] HEX_BYTES FIELD_NAME (VALUE), minimum 8 documented NP3 fields labeled, NP3-only validation with clear error messages for text formats.</snippet>
      </artifact>
      <artifact>
        <path>docs/architecture.md</path>
        <title>Architecture</title>
        <section>Epic to Architecture Mapping Project Structure</section>
        <snippet>Recipe uses hub-and-spoke pattern with UniversalRecipe intermediate representation. Epic 5 extends CLI interface from Epic 3. New internal/inspect/ module for inspection tools. Structure cmd/{cli,tui,wasm}/ plus internal/ plus web/. CLI uses Cobra framework with shared converter.Convert() API.</snippet>
      </artifact>
      <artifact>
        <path>docs/tech-spec-epic-1.md</path>
        <title>Epic Technical Specification Core Conversion Engine</title>
        <section>Module internal/formats/np3</section>
        <snippet>NP3 format specification with fixed size files, magic bytes NCP at offset 0-2, version at 3-6, preset name at 20-60. Parameters extracted via heuristic analysis of raw parameter bytes offsets 64-80, color data 100-300, tone curve data 150-500. Achieves 95 percent accuracy through round-trip testing.</snippet>
      </artifact>
      <artifact>
        <path>docs/stories/5-1-parameter-inspection-tool.md</path>
        <title>Story 5.1 Parameter Inspection Tool</title>
        <section>Foundation for internal/inspect/ package</section>
        <snippet>Story 5-1 establishes internal/inspect/ package and recipe inspect command. Story 5-2 adds binary.go to same package for hex dump functionality. Shared CLI command structure with different modes, default JSON or --binary for hex dump.</snippet>
      </artifact>
      <artifact>
        <path>docs/stories/1-2-np3-binary-parser.md</path>
        <title>Story 1.2 NP3 Binary Parser</title>
        <section>NP3 format reverse engineering field extraction</section>
        <snippet>NP3 binary parser implements heuristic analysis for parameter extraction. Magic bytes NCP at 0-2, minimum 300 bytes. Raw parameter bytes at offsets 64-80 with 128-offset conversion. Sharpness 66-70, Brightness 71-75, Hue 76-79. Color data analysis for saturation, tone curve analysis for contrast.</snippet>
      </artifact>
      <artifact>
        <path>docs/stories/1-3-np3-binary-generator.md</path>
        <title>Story 1.3 NP3 Binary Generator</title>
        <section>NP3 encoding strategy raw byte generation</section>
        <snippet>Generator reverses parser heuristic approach. Raw byte encoding Sharpness formula params.sharpening times 255 divided by 9 minus 128, Brightness brightness times 128.0, Hue hue times 128 divided by 9. Color data generation for saturation formula saturation plus 1 times 15 RGB triplets. Tone curve generation for contrast with overlap accounting.</snippet>
      </artifact>
    </docs>
    <code>
      <artifact>
        <path>internal/formats/np3/parse.go</path>
        <kind>parser</kind>
        <symbol>extractParameters</symbol>
        <lines>122-250</lines>
        <reason>NP3 parameter extraction function contains all known byte offset mappings. Critical reference for building np3FieldMap constant. Shows raw parameter bytes 64-80, color data analysis 100-300, tone curve analysis 150-500.</reason>
      </artifact>
      <artifact>
        <path>internal/formats/np3/parse.go</path>
        <kind>parser</kind>
        <symbol>Parse</symbol>
        <lines>46-90</lines>
        <reason>Main NP3 parsing entry point. Shows file structure validation for magic bytes and minimum size. Demonstrates error handling pattern to follow in binary dump error cases.</reason>
      </artifact>
      <artifact>
        <path>internal/formats/np3/generate.go</path>
        <kind>generator</kind>
        <symbol>encodeBinary</symbol>
        <lines>125-160</lines>
        <reason>Shows complete NP3 file structure with magic bytes NCP at 0-2, version at 3-6, preset name at 20-59, raw parameter bytes starting at 64. Exact byte offsets for field map.</reason>
      </artifact>
      <artifact>
        <path>internal/formats/np3/generate.go</path>
        <kind>generator</kind>
        <symbol>writeRawParameterBytes</symbol>
        <lines>167-230</lines>
        <reason>Documents raw byte encoding formulas for sharpness 66-70, brightness 71-75, hue 76-79. Shows reverse normalization formulas needed for displaying human-readable values in hex dump annotations.</reason>
      </artifact>
      <artifact>
        <path>internal/formats/np3/generate.go</path>
        <kind>generator</kind>
        <symbol>convertToNP3Parameters</symbol>
        <lines>55-122</lines>
        <reason>Shows parameter range conversions and normalization formulas. Contrast universalValue divided by 33 equals np3Value range -3 to +3. Saturation same formula. Brightness maps to Exposure field -1.0 to +1.0. Essential for field value formatting.</reason>
      </artifact>
      <artifact>
        <path>cmd/cli/main.go</path>
        <kind>cli</kind>
        <symbol>main</symbol>
        <lines>1-50</lines>
        <reason>Cobra CLI root command structure. Shows how to add new subcommands. Story 5-2 will add inspect.go to this CLI structure following same pattern.</reason>
      </artifact>
      <artifact>
        <path>internal/models/recipe.go</path>
        <kind>model</kind>
        <symbol>UniversalRecipe</symbol>
        <lines>1-100</lines>
        <reason>Core data model. While binary dump operates on raw bytes, understanding UniversalRecipe fields helps map to NP3 parameters for annotation context.</reason>
      </artifact>
    </code>
    <dependencies>
      <go>
        <package name="fmt" version="stdlib">String formatting for hex dump output</package>
        <package name="bytes" version="stdlib">Byte manipulation for hex encoding</package>
        <package name="encoding/hex" version="stdlib">Hex encoding utilities</package>
        <package name="strings" version="stdlib">strings.Builder for efficient output construction</package>
        <package name="os" version="stdlib">File I/O operations</package>
        <package name="github.com/spf13/cobra" version="v1.10.1">CLI framework for inspect command integration</package>
      </go>
    </dependencies>
  </artifacts>

  <constraints>
Binary Mode NP3-Only works ONLY with NP3 files not XMP or lrtemplate text formats. No Parsing Overhead operates directly on raw bytes without calling NP3 parser for performance. Read-Only Operation inspection only does not modify files or parse into UniversalRecipe. Performance Target under 10ms for typical NP3 files under 50KB faster than JSON mode. Memory Limit under 5 MB total achieved through simple hex formatting. CLI Pattern Consistency follows Epic 3 patterns using Cobra framework consistent flag names error handling with ConversionError type. Graceful Degradation corrupt NP3 files produce partial hex dump with warnings not crashes. Unknown Byte Handling fields not in np3FieldMap shown as raw hex without annotation for extensibility. Field Map Completeness start with minimum 8 required fields expand based on Epic 1 reverse engineering. Output Format plain text hex dump suitable for piping redirection file storage. Error Messages user-friendly explanations not technical jargon. Standard CLI Behavior --output flag overwrites without confirmation creates parent directories follows Unix exit codes.
  </constraints>

  <interfaces>
New Internal API internal/inspect/binary.go provides BinaryDump function signature (data []byte, format string) returning (string, error). Creates annotated hex dump for NP3 files, returns error if format not np3. Field Map Constant np3FieldMap map[int]string contains entries offset 0x0000 Magic Bytes NCP signature, 0x0003 Version 4 bytes, 0x0014 Preset Name offsets 20-60 null-terminated ASCII up to 40 chars, 0x0042 Sharpness raw offsets 66-70 5 bytes same value, 0x0047 Brightness raw offsets 71-75 5 bytes same value, 0x004C Hue raw offsets 76-79 4 bytes same value, 0x0064 Color Data Start offset 100 RGB triplets for saturation, 0x0096 Tone Curve Start offset 150 paired values for contrast, plus additional fields from Epic 1 reverse engineering. Helper Function formatFieldValue signature (offset int, rawByte byte) returning string converts raw byte to human-readable value based on field type returning formatted string like Contrast (+15, raw: 143). CLI Command Extension cmd/cli/inspect.go adds new flag inspectCmd.Flags().Bool binary false with description Show hex dump with field annotations NP3 only. Integration Pattern runInspect function checks binaryMode flag validates NP3 format returns error if not calls inspect.BinaryDump with data and format handles output to stdout or file. Reused Interfaces from Epic 1 include no direct parser calls as binary dump operates on raw bytes does not invoke np3.Parse, field offset reference uses knowledge from parse.go and generate.go to build np3FieldMap, error handling pattern follows ConversionError type for consistency.
  </interfaces>

  <tests>
    <standards>
Go standard testing framework with table-driven tests. Benchmark tests for performance validation using testing.B. All tests follow Epic 1 pattern with package_test.go files containing comprehensive test cases. Mock data for unit tests and real sample files for integration tests. Code coverage target at least 90 percent for internal/inspect/binary.go. Performance benchmarks validate under 10ms target on reference hardware.
    </standards>
    <locations>
internal/inspect/binary_test.go contains unit tests and benchmarks for BinaryDump function. cmd/cli/inspect_test.go contains CLI integration tests for --binary flag to be added or extended. testdata/ reuses existing NP3 sample files for validation with no new test data needed.
    </locations>
    <ideas>
Unit Tests in internal/inspect/binary_test.go include TestBinaryDump_Format verifying output matches [0xOFFSET] HEX pattern with correct offsets and uppercase hex, TestBinaryDump_KnownFields verifying minimum 8 fields annotated Magic Version Contrast Brightness Saturation Hue Sharpness Preset Name, TestBinaryDump_NonNP3Error verifying error returned for XMP and lrtemplate formats with error message mentioning NP3 only, TestBinaryDump_CorruptFile testing graceful degradation with invalid magic bytes warning but continuing, TestBinaryDump_CompleteCoverage verifying all bytes displayed without truncation, TestFormatFieldValue testing normalization formulas contrast 143 to +15 brightness 128 to 0.

Performance Benchmarks include BenchmarkBinaryDump validating under 10ms target with typical NP3 file approximately 10KB, BenchmarkBinaryDump_LargeFile testing with maximum expected NP3 size approximately 50KB, memory profiling verifying under 5 MB usage with go test -memprofile.

CLI Integration Tests in cmd/cli/inspect_test.go include TestInspectBinary_NP3 end-to-end test with real NP3 file verifying hex dump output, TestInspectBinary_XMPError verifying clear error when using --binary with XMP file, TestInspectBinary_LrtemplateError verifying clear error with lrtemplate, TestInspectBinary_OutputFile verifying --output flag creates file with hex dump content, TestInspectBinary_StdoutPipe verifying output can be piped with grep head tail.

Real Sample File Tests include TestBinaryDump_AllSamples iterating all NP3 files in examples/np3/ verifying no crashes and non-empty output, comparing hex dump annotations to parser output for validation ensuring contrast value in hex matches parsed value.
    </ideas>
  </tests>
</story-context>
