<story-context id="bmad/bmm/workflows/4-implementation/story-context/template" v="1.0">
  <metadata>
    <epicId>7</epicId>
    <storyId>7.3</storyId>
    <title>FAQ Documentation</title>
    <status>drafted</status>
    <generatedAt>2025-11-06</generatedAt>
    <generator>BMAD Story Context Workflow</generator>
    <sourceStoryPath>docs/stories/7-3-faq-documentation.md</sourceStoryPath>
  </metadata>

  <story>
    <asA>photographer with questions about Recipe's legality, privacy, and conversion quality</asA>
    <iWant>a comprehensive FAQ section answering common questions</iWant>
    <soThat>I can make informed decisions about using Recipe and understand its limitations before
      converting my presets</soThat>
    <tasks>
      ### Task 1: Create FAQ Document (AC-1, AC-2, AC-3, AC-4, AC-5)
      - Create `docs/faq.md` with complete FAQ structure (Legal, Privacy, Conversion Quality,
      Technical Questions)
      - Write legal answer (reverse engineering, fair use, private use recommendation)
      - Write privacy answer (WASM client-side, zero uploads, user verifiable)
      - Write accuracy answer (95%+ metrics, validation methods, best practices)
      - Write format limitations answer (unmappable features, NP3 constraints)
      - Add technical questions (browsers, offline use, bug reports)
      - Follow Short Answer → Details → References structure

      ### Task 2: Link FAQ from Landing Page (AC-1, AC-5)
      - Update `web/index.html` with FAQ section and link to docs/faq.md
      - Choose approach: FAQ link with bullet list (simpler) OR embed top 3 questions

      ### Task 3: Update README.md with FAQ Link (AC-5)
      - Add FAQ section to README.md with top 3 questions and link to full FAQ

      ### Task 4: Cross-Reference FAQ with Existing Documentation (AC-1, AC-2, AC-3, AC-4)
      - Verify Legal Disclaimer alignment (Story 7-4)
      - Verify Privacy Messaging alignment (Story 2-9)
      - Verify Format Compatibility Matrix alignment (Story 7-2)
      - Verify Accuracy Metrics alignment (Epic 1 Retrospective)

      ### Task 5: Add FAQ to Documentation Index (AC-6)
      - Update `docs/index.md` with FAQ entry (if index exists)

      ### Task 6: Deploy and Verify FAQ Accessibility
      - Commit changes to Git
      - Verify Cloudflare Pages deployment
      - Test FAQ accessibility from landing page and README
      - Test mobile-responsive design
      - Test all external and internal links
    </tasks>
  </story>

  <acceptanceCriteria>
    ### AC-1: FAQ Answers "Is this legal? (reverse engineering)"
    Question clearly addresses legal concerns with answer including:
    - Reverse engineering context explained (Nikon .np3 undocumented)
    - Fair use and interoperability exemptions cited
    - Research and educational purposes (DMCA 1201)
    - No affiliation with Nikon/Adobe stated
    - Recommendation: Private use only until legal assessment complete
    - Honest tone: Not legal advice disclaimer, conservative approach
    - Links to DMCA 1201 exemptions, Fair use doctrine, Legal disclaimer (Story 7-4)

    ### AC-2: FAQ Answers "Is my data private?"
    Question directly addresses privacy concerns with answer including:
    - Confirms YES, files remain 100% private
    - WebAssembly architecture: All processing client-side
    - Zero server uploads, no network requests during conversion
    - No tracking, no analytics, no cookies, no data collection
    - Simple technical explanation (WASM runs on user's computer)
    - Proof: Network monitoring shows zero uploads
    - Links to Privacy messaging (Story 2-9), Architecture documentation

    ### AC-3: FAQ Answers "Why doesn't [feature] convert?"
    Question addresses user confusion with answer including:
    - Format limitations explained (NP3 simpler than XMP/lrtemplate)
    - Examples of unmappable features: Tone Curves, Grain, Vignette, Split Toning, Clarity, Dehaze
    - What DOES convert (95%+ accuracy): Exposure, Contrast, Saturation, HSL (24 parameters),
    Temperature, Tint, Sharpness
    - Recipe's behavior: Warns user, converts what it can, skips unmappable features
    - Links to Format Compatibility Matrix (Story 7-2) for complete parameter list

    ### AC-4: FAQ Answers "How accurate is conversion?"
    Question addresses conversion quality with answer including:
    - 95%+ accuracy target for core adjustments
    - Accuracy breakdown: Direct mappings (98%+), Approximations (90-95%), Unmappable (N/A)
    - Validation methods: Round-trip testing, Visual validation, 1,501 sample files tested
    - What affects accuracy: Direct 1:1 mappings vs approximations vs format limitations
    - Best practices: Always visually validate, understand limitations, expect 95%+ for core
    - Links to Format Compatibility Matrix, Epic 1 Retrospective

    ### AC-5: Answers are Clear and Concise
    All answers follow structure:
    - Short Answer First: 1-2 sentence immediate answer
    - Length: 2-8 paragraphs (not too brief, not overwhelming)
    - Clear Structure: Headings, tables, bullet lists for scannable content
    - Non-Technical Language: Avoids jargon, defines technical terms
    - Actionable: Provides next steps, links to details, recommendations

    ### AC-6: FAQ Updated Based on User Feedback (Post-Launch)
    Process defined for continuous improvement:
    - Monitor GitHub Issues for common questions (3+ times → Add to FAQ)
    - Draft answer based on existing responses
    - Review for clarity and accuracy
    - Update FAQ document
    - Link to FAQ in future Issue responses
    - Include "Last Updated" date at top of FAQ
  </acceptanceCriteria>

  <artifacts>
    <docs>
      <doc>
        <path>docs/PRD.md</path>
        <title>Product Requirements Document</title>
        <section>FR-7: Documentation and User Support</section>
        <snippet>FR-7.3: FAQ - Answer common questions: Is this legal? (reverse engineering), Is my
          data private? (yes, WASM), Why doesn't [feature] convert? (format limitations), How
          accurate is conversion? (95%+)</snippet>
      </doc>
      <doc>
        <path>docs/PRD.md</path>
        <title>Product Requirements Document</title>
        <section>Success Criteria - User Success</section>
        <snippet>Users confidently convert proprietary/purchased presets without sharing them. FAQ's
          privacy answer directly addresses this success criterion by explaining WASM architecture
          in user-friendly terms.</snippet>
      </doc>
      <doc>
        <path>docs/tech-spec-epic-7.md</path>
        <title>Epic 7 Technical Specification</title>
        <section>FR-7.3: FAQ Documentation (Story 7-3)</section>
        <snippet>AC-1 through AC-6 define FAQ requirements: legal, privacy, accuracy, format
          limitations, conciseness, update process. All answers 2-4 sentences, non-technical
          language, links to technical details.</snippet>
      </doc>
      <doc>
        <path>docs/architecture.md</path>
        <title>Architecture Documentation</title>
        <section>Security Architecture - Privacy-First Design</section>
        <snippet>All conversions happen client-side via WebAssembly. No network requests during
          conversion. No analytics, no telemetry, no tracking. Files never uploaded to any server.
          WASM sandbox prevents malicious file attacks.</snippet>
      </doc>
      <doc>
        <path>docs/stories/2-9-privacy-messaging.md</path>
        <title>Story 2-9: Privacy Messaging</title>
        <section>Privacy FAQ Section</section>
        <snippet>6 Q and A items covering: server uploads (No), tracking (No), WASM explanation
          (client-side processing), auditability (open source GitHub), analytics (none), browser
          safety (sandboxed). WebAssembly explained as mini-application running entirely on your
          computer.</snippet>
      </doc>
      <doc>
        <path>docs/epic-1-retrospective.md</path>
        <title>Epic 1 Retrospective</title>
        <section>Conversion Accuracy Validation</section>
        <snippet>1,501 sample files tested (22 NP3, 913 XMP, 544 lrtemplate). Round-trip testing
          validates parameter equality. Visual validation confirms 95%+ accuracy for core
          adjustments. Direct mappings achieve 98%+ accuracy (Exposure, Contrast, Saturation, HSL).</snippet>
      </doc>
      <doc>
        <path>docs/stories/7-1-landing-page.md</path>
        <title>Story 7-1: Landing Page</title>
        <section>AC-5: FAQ Section Linked or Embedded</section>
        <snippet>FAQ covers 4 minimum questions: Is this legal? Is my data private? Why doesn't
          [feature] convert? How accurate is conversion? Embedded on landing page (top 3-5
          questions) or link to separate FAQ page.</snippet>
      </doc>
      <doc>
        <path>docs/stories/7-2-format-compatibility-matrix.md</path>
        <title>Story 7-2: Format Compatibility Matrix</title>
        <section>Unmappable Features</section>
        <snippet>NP3 does NOT support: Tone Curves (no curve support), Grain (texture effects),
          Vignette (edge darkening), Split Toning (shadow/highlight tints), Clarity (mid-tone
          contrast), Dehaze (atmospheric haze). Recipe warns user when parameters can't be mapped.</snippet>
      </doc>
    </docs>
    <code>
      <artifact>
        <path>web/index.html</path>
        <kind>HTML template</kind>
        <symbol>FAQ section integration point</symbol>
        <lines>88-129</lines>
        <reason>Landing page where FAQ link or embed will be added (Story 7-1 created structure,
          Story 7-3 adds FAQ section)</reason>
      </artifact>
      <artifact>
        <path>web/static/privacy-messaging.js</path>
        <kind>JavaScript module</kind>
        <symbol>Privacy messaging functions</symbol>
        <lines>1-98</lines>
        <reason>Story 2-9 implemented privacy FAQ (6 Q and A items). Story 7-3 should reference or
          extend this content for comprehensive FAQ.</reason>
      </artifact>
      <artifact>
        <path>README.md</path>
        <kind>Documentation</kind>
        <symbol>README structure</symbol>
        <lines>1-100</lines>
        <reason>README will receive FAQ section with top 3 questions and link to full FAQ (Task 3)</reason>
      </artifact>
      <artifact>
        <path>docs/index.md</path>
        <kind>Documentation index</kind>
        <symbol>Documentation navigation</symbol>
        <lines>1-50</lines>
        <reason>Documentation index will receive FAQ entry if file exists (Task 5)</reason>
      </artifact>
    </code>
    <dependencies>
      <dependency>
        <name>None (Go standard library only for core logic)</name>
        <version>Go 1.24+</version>
        <purpose>No external dependencies for FAQ documentation - pure markdown content</purpose>
      </dependency>
    </dependencies>
  </artifacts>

  <constraints>
    ### Development Constraints
    1. **English-Only Documentation**: English language only for MVP (i18n deferred per PRD)
    2. **Markdown Format**: All documentation in Markdown (.md files) for simplicity and GitHub
    rendering
    3. **No Build Tools**: Static HTML/CSS, no build step for web interface (vanilla JavaScript)
    4. **Conservative Legal Stance**: No legal advice, recommend private use, acknowledge
    uncertainty
    5. **Privacy-First Messaging**: Reinforce WASM architecture, zero tracking, zero uploads

    ### Architectural Constraints
    1. **Progressive Disclosure**: FAQ starts with Short Answer, links to details for deep dives
    2. **Cross-Reference Integrity**: FAQ must align with Story 2-9 (Privacy), Story 7-2
    (Compatibility), Story 7-4 (Legal Disclaimer)
    3. **Mobile Responsive**: All FAQ content must be readable on mobile devices (inherited from
    Epic 2 Story 2-10)
    4. **Accessibility**: Keyboard navigation, screen reader compatible, ARIA attributes

    ### Content Quality Constraints
    1. **Non-Technical Language**: Photographer-friendly, avoid developer jargon
    2. **Accuracy**: 95%+ metrics must match PRD targets and Epic 1 validation results
    3. **Honesty**: Transparent about limitations, no overpromising on conversion fidelity
    4. **Actionable**: Every answer provides next steps or links to supporting documentation

    ### Integration Constraints
    1. **Story 7-1 Dependency**: Landing page structure must exist before FAQ link can be added
    2. **Story 2-9 Reference**: Privacy FAQ already exists in web interface, Story 7-3 creates
    comprehensive docs/faq.md version
    3. **Story 7-4 Coordination**: Legal disclaimer will formalize FAQ legal answer (FAQ references
    future disclaimer)
    4. **Cloudflare Pages**: Deployment workflow (Story 7-5) will publish FAQ automatically on push
    to main
  </constraints>

  <interfaces>
    ### User-Facing Interfaces
    **Landing Page FAQ Section** (`web/index.html`)
    - Input: User clicks FAQ link in navigation or privacy badge
    - Output: Smooth scroll to FAQ section or jump to docs/faq.md
    - Format: HTML anchor link with `href="#faq"` or `href="docs/faq.md"`

    **README.md FAQ Section**
    - Input: Developer/user reads GitHub repository README
    - Output: Top 3 FAQ questions with links to full FAQ
    - Format: Markdown with inline questions and `[View Full FAQ →](docs/faq.md)` link
    **Documentation Index** (`docs/index.md`)
    - Input: User navigates documentation
    - Output: FAQ listed in User Documentation section
    - Format: Markdown list item `- [FAQ](faq.md) - Frequently asked questions`

    ### Internal Documentation References
    **Cross-References to Existing Docs:**
    - Story 2-9 Privacy Messaging: Link from FAQ privacy answer
    - Story 7-2 Format Compatibility Matrix: Link from FAQ format limitations answer
    - Story 7-4 Legal Disclaimer: Link from FAQ legal answer (when available)
    - Epic 1 Retrospective: Cite accuracy validation results in FAQ accuracy answer
    - Architecture Documentation: Link to WASM security section from FAQ technical questions
    **External Links:**
    - DMCA 1201 Exemptions: https://www.copyright.gov/1201/
    - Fair Use Doctrine: https://www.copyright.gov/fair-use/
    - WebAssembly: https://webassembly.org/
    - GitHub Repository: https://github.com/{user}/recipe
  </interfaces>

  <tests>
    <standards>
      ### Testing Standards for Story 7-3
      **Manual Testing (Primary Method):**
      - Content Accuracy: Cross-reference FAQ answers with PRD, Tech Spec, Epic 1 implementation
      - Link Validation: Click all internal and external links to verify functionality
      - Readability: Non-technical user comprehension test (ask photographer to read FAQ, verify
      understanding)
      - Mobile Responsive: Test on phone/tablet (readable, no horizontal scroll)

      **Content Validation:**
      - Legal Answer: Verify conservative approach (private use recommended, no legal guarantees)
      - Privacy Answer: Verify WASM architecture explained accurately (zero uploads, client-side)
      - Accuracy Answer: Verify 95%+ metric matches PRD and Epic 1 validation results
      - Format Limitations: Verify unmappable features list matches Story 7-2 compatibility matrix
      **Acceptance Validation:**
      - All 6 ACs verified (legal, privacy, accuracy, format limitations, conciseness, update
      process)
      - Links working (FAQ accessible from landing page, README, docs index)
      - Non-technical user can understand answers (&lt;2 minutes to find answer)
    </standards>
    <locations>
      <location>docs/faq.md (new file to be created)</location>
      <location>web/index.html (FAQ section or link to be added)</location>
      <location>README.md (FAQ section to be added)</location>
      <location>docs/index.md (FAQ entry to be added if file exists)</location>
    </locations>
    <ideas>
      <idea ac="AC-1">
        **Test Legal Answer Accuracy:**
        - Verify reverse engineering context explained clearly (Nikon .np3 undocumented)
        - Verify fair use exemptions cited (DMCA 1201, interoperability)
        - Verify conservative recommendation (private use only)
        - Verify "not legal advice" disclaimer present
        - Verify links to DMCA 1201 and Fair Use working
      </idea>
      <idea ac="AC-2">
        **Test Privacy Answer Accuracy:**
        - Verify WASM architecture explained in simple terms
        - Verify zero uploads confirmed explicitly
        - Verify user can verify privacy claim (network monitoring suggestion)
        - Verify links to Story 2-9 privacy messaging and architecture docs working
        - Ask non-technical user: "Does Recipe upload your files?" (Answer should be "No")
      </idea>
      <idea ac="AC-3">
        **Test Format Limitations Answer:**
        - Verify NP3 limitations explained (simpler in-camera format)
        - Verify unmappable features listed with examples (Tone Curves, Grain, Vignette)
        - Verify what DOES convert listed (95%+ accuracy parameters)
        - Verify link to Format Compatibility Matrix (Story 7-2) working
        - Ask user: "Why doesn't Grain convert?" (Answer should reference NP3 format limitation)
      </idea>
      <idea ac="AC-4">
        **Test Accuracy Answer Completeness:**
        - Verify 95%+ accuracy target stated explicitly
        - Verify accuracy breakdown table present (Direct/Approximations/Unmappable)
        - Verify validation methods explained (round-trip, visual, 1,501 samples)
        - Verify best practices recommended (visual validation)
        - Verify links to compatibility matrix and retrospective working
      </idea>
      <idea ac="AC-5">
        **Test Answer Clarity and Structure:**
        - Verify all answers have "Short Answer" section (1-2 sentences)
        - Verify answer length appropriate (2-8 paragraphs, not overwhelming)
        - Verify scannable structure (headings, tables, bullet lists)
        - Verify non-technical language (no unexplained jargon)
        - Ask non-technical user to read FAQ, verify they understand answers in &lt;30 seconds per
        question
      </idea>
      <idea ac="AC-6">
        **Test Post-Launch Update Process:**
        - Verify process documented for adding new questions from GitHub Issues
        - Verify "Last Updated" date present at top of FAQ
        - Verify FAQ maintenance process clear (monitor Issues, add common questions)
      </idea>
      <idea ac="Integration">
        **Test Cross-Reference Integrity:**
        - Verify FAQ legal answer aligns with Story 7-4 legal disclaimer (if complete)
        - Verify FAQ privacy answer aligns with Story 2-9 privacy messaging
        - Verify FAQ format limitations align with Story 7-2 compatibility matrix
        - Verify FAQ accuracy metrics match Epic 1 retrospective validation results
        - Check for contradictions between FAQ and other documentation
      </idea>
      <idea ac="Accessibility">
        **Test FAQ Accessibility:**
        - Test FAQ link in landing page (click → jump to FAQ section or docs/faq.md)
        - Test README FAQ links (click → open docs/faq.md)
        - Test all external links (DMCA, Fair Use, WebAssembly, GitHub)
        - Test mobile responsive (FAQ readable on phone, no horizontal scroll)
        - Test keyboard navigation (all links accessible via Tab key)
      </idea>
    </ideas>
  </tests>
</story-context>